This walkthrough builds an interactive
account-risk assistant with Oracle AI
Database, AG-UI, A2UI, the Oracle Database
MCP Java Toolkit, and an optional MCP App.
The result is a governed workflow, not
just a text answer.
The browser receives AG-UI events and A2UI
interface updates.
The Java service owns orchestration,
validation, and human approval.
The MCP Toolkit exposes governed database
capabilities that multiple agents and
MCP-compatible clients can reuse.
The default application now launches the
pinned Oracle Database MCP Java Toolkit
over standard input and output.
It initializes the MCP session, verifies
the server identity, and fails closed
unless exactly five account-risk tools are
available.
The Toolkit configuration enables
purpose-built reads, action identifier
reservation, the procedure-backed write,
and a verification count.
All database values are binds.
Broad query, write, table, and
administration tools are not enabled.
Oracle AI Database stores the accounts,
risk evidence, and audited follow-up
actions.
The approved MCP tool calls an input-only
procedure that validates inputs, locks the
selected account, inserts one action, and
updates its status atomically.
AG-UI streams standard run, text,
tool-call, state, and error events from
the Java service to the browser.
A2UI envelopes travel inside an AG-UI
custom event named a2ui.message, keeping
transport and interface responsibilities
distinct.
The browser accepts only A2UI version zero
point nine point one, the expected surface
and catalog, and a small component
allowlist.
Generated values enter the page as text,
so the agent cannot inject executable HTML
or JavaScript.
For compatible conversational hosts, the
optional MCP App registers a sandboxed
dashboard resource.
Sandboxing is part of the MCP Apps host
model, not merely a demo choice.
Structured account data crosses the host
bridge, while database credentials do not.
In the application, the user sets a risk
threshold and row limit.
The AG-UI event rail shows run and MCP
tool activity, while A2UI renders
selectable account cards, risk
explanations, and approval controls.
Approval is bound to the actor, returned
account set, and a short-lived single-use
identifier.
Approve invokes the bounded MCP tools and
displays the committed action identifier.
Cancel consumes the approval without
creating a database action.
Each component keeps one clear
responsibility: AG-UI streams, A2UI
describes trusted controls, MCP Apps add
rich sandboxed experiences, the MCP
Toolkit exposes reusable governed
capabilities, and Oracle AI Database
governs data and transactions.